<!DOCTYPE node PUBLIC
    "-//freedesktop//DTD D-BUS Object Introspection 1.0//EN"
     "http://www.freedesktop.org/standards/dbus/1.0/introspect.dtd">

<node xmlns:doc="http://www.freedesktop.org/dbus/1.0/doc.dtd">
  <interface name="io.github.geopm">
    <doc:doc>
      <doc:description>
        <doc:para>The GEOPM DBus API enables a client to make measurements from the
hardware platform and set hardware control parameters.  Fine grained
permissions management for both measurements (signals) and controls is
configurable by system administrators.
        </doc:para>
      </doc:description>
    </doc:doc>
    <method name="TopoGetCache">
      <arg direction="out" name="result" type="s">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Contents of the topology cache file that defines
the system topology.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Return the contents of the PlatformTopo cache file.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Create the PlatformTopo cache file if it does not exist and
then return the contents of the file as a string.  This
provides all the information required to associate all domains
with CPUs.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformGetGroupAccess">
      <arg direction="in" name="group" type="s">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Name of group
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" name="access_lists" type="(asas)">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>list(str), list(str): Signal and control allowed lists, both in sorted order.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Get the signal and control access lists
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Read the list of allowed signals and controls for the
specified group.  If the group is None or the empty string
then the default lists of allowed signals and controls are
returned.

The values are securely read from files located in
/etc/geopm using the secure_read_file() interface.

If no secure file exist for the specified group, then two
empty lists are returned.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformSetGroupAccess">
      <arg direction="in" name="group" type="s">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Name of group
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="allowed_signals" type="as">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Signal names that are allowed
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="allowed_controls" type="as">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Control names that are allowed
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Set signals and controls in the allowed lists
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Write the list of allowed signals and controls for the
specified group.  If the group is None or the empty string
then the default lists of allowed signals and controls are
updated.

The values are securely written atomically to files located in
/etc/geopm using the secure_make_dirs() and
secure_make_file() interfaces.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformSetGroupAccessSignals">
      <arg direction="in" name="group" type="s">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Name of group
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="allowed_signals" type="as">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Signal names that are allowed
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Set signals and controls in the allowed lists
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Write the list of allowed signals and controls for the
specified group.  If the group is None or the empty string
then the default lists of allowed signals and controls are
updated.

The values are securely written atomically to files located in
/etc/geopm using the secure_make_dirs() and
secure_make_file() interfaces.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformSetGroupAccessControls">
      <arg direction="in" name="group" type="s">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Name of group
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="allowed_controls" type="as">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Control names that are allowed
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Set signals and controls in the allowed lists
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Write the list of allowed signals and controls for the
specified group.  If the group is None or the empty string
then the default lists of allowed signals and controls are
updated.

The values are securely written atomically to files located in
/etc/geopm using the secure_make_dirs() and
secure_make_file() interfaces.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformGetUserAccess">
      <arg direction="out" name="access_lists" type="(asas)">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>list(str), list(str): Signal and control allowed lists, both in sorted order.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Get the list of all of the signals and controls that are
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>accessible to the specified user.

Returns the default access lists that apply to all non-root
users if the empty string is provided.

All available signals and controls are returned if the caller
specifies the a pid with CAP_SYSADMIN.  A RuntimeError is
raised if the user does not exist on the system.

When a user requests a signal or control through one of the
other PlatformService methods, they are restricted to the
union of the default allowed lists and the allowed lists for
all Unix groups that the user belongs to.  These combined
lists are what this method returns.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformGetAllAccess">
      <arg direction="out" name="access_lists" type="(asas)">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>list(str), list(str): All supported signals and controls, in sorted order.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Get all of the signals and controls that the service supports.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Returns the list of all signals and controls supported by the
service.  The lists returned are independent of the access
controls; therefore, calling get_all_access() is equivalent
to calling get_user_access() for a user with CAP_SYSADMIN.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformGetSignalInfo">
      <arg direction="in" name="signal_names" type="as">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>List of signal names to query
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" name="info" type="a(ssiiii)">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>list(tuple((str), (str), (int), (int), (int), (int))):
name (str): The signal name specified by the caller

description (str): A human-readable description of
                   what the signal measures.

domain_type (int): One of the geopmpy.topo.DOMAIN_*
                   integers corresponding to a domain
                   type where the signal is natively
                   supported.

aggregation (int): One of the geopm::Agg::m_type_e
                   enum values defined in Agg.hpp that
                   specifies how to aggregate the
                   signal over domains.

format_type (int): One of the geopm::string_format_e
                   enum values defined in Helper.hpp
                   that specifies how to convert the
                   signal value to a human readable
                   string.

behavior (int): One of the
                IOGroup::m_signal_behavior_e enum
                values that specifies how the signal
                changes over time.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>For each specified signal name, return a tuple of information.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>The caller provides a list of signal names.  This method returns
a list of the same length which consists of a tuple of information
for each signal.

The method will raise a RuntimeError if any of the requested
signal names are not supported by the service.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformGetControlInfo">
      <arg direction="in" name="control_names" type="as">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>List of control names to query
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" name="info" type="a(ssi)">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>list(tuple((str), (str), (int))):
name (str): The control name specified by the caller

description (str): A human-readable description of the
                   effect of setting the control.

domain_type (int): One of the geopmpy.topo.DOMAIN_*
                   integers corresponding to a domain
                   type that is the finest available
                   granularity for the control.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>For each specified control name, return a tuple of information.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>The caller provides a list of control names.  This method returns
a list of the same length which consists of a tuple of information
for each control.

The method will raise a RuntimeError if any of the requested
control names are not supported by the service.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformLockControl">
     <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Block all write-mode sessions.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>A call to this method will end any currently running
write-mode session and block the creation of any new
write-mode sessions.  Use the unlock_control() method to
enable write-mode sessions to begin again.

Calls to this method through the DBus interface will be
blocked for all non-root users due to the rules established by
the "io.github.geopm.conf" DBus configuration file.

Until write-mode sessions are re-enabled, any calls to
write_control() or calls to start_batch() with a non-empty
control_config parameter will raise a RuntimeError.

The default system configuration may be updated by the system
administrator while write-mode is locked.  For instance, the
system administrator may use the geopmwrite command-line tool
as user root between calls to lock_control() and
unlock_control().  These changes will be reflected by the
save/restore executed by the service for the next client
write-mode session after the controls are unlocked.

No action is taken and no error is raised if controls are already
disabled when this method is called.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformUnlockControl">
     <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Unblock access to create new write-mode sessions.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>A call to this method will re-enable write-mode sessions to be
created after they were previously disabled by a call to
lock_control().

Although new sessions may be created after a call to
unlock_control(), write-mode sessions that were ended due to
previous calls to lock_control() will remain closed.

No action is taken and no error is raised if controls are already
enabled when this method is called.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformOpenSession">
     <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Open a new session for the client thread.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>The creation of a session is the first step that a client
thread makes to interact with the GEOPM service.  Each Linux
thread has a unique PID, and this PID can be associated with
at most one GEOPM service session.  The session is ended by
passing the client PID to the close_session() method.  The
session will also be ended if the client thread terminates for
any reason.

The client PID may attempt to open a new session multiple
times.  In this case a reference count records the number of
calls to open the session by the client PID.  Each call to
open a session is expected to be paired with a call to close
the session.  When the reference count falls to zero, all
resources associated with the session are released.

Incrementing the reference count is an abstraction for the
client.  The client itself cannot have more than a single open
connection at once, so when requesting a new session, other
than incrementing the counter, nothing else happens.

All sessions are opened in read-mode, and may later be
promoted to write-mode.  This promotion will occur with the
first successful call requiring access to controls.  This
includes any calls to write_control() or calls to
start_batch() with a non-empty control_config.  These calls
will fail if there is an active write-mode session opened by
another thread.

Prior to being promoted to write-mode, the current value for
all controls that are supported by the GEOPM service will be
recorded.  This record enables the service to restore all
controls when the write-mode session ends.

Permissions for the session's access to signals and controls
are determined based on the policy for the user when
the session is first opened.  Calling the set_group_access()
method to alter the policy will not affect active sessions.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformCloseSession">
     <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Close an active session for the client process.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>After closing a session, the client process is required to
call open_session() again before using any of the client-facing
member functions.

Closing an active session will remove the record of which
signals and controls the client process has access to; thus,
this record is updated to reflect changes to the policy when the
next session is opened by the process.

When closing a write-mode session, the control values that were
recorded when the session was promoted to write-mode are restored.

A client PID may attempt to open a session multiple times and
this is tracked with a reference count as described in the
documentation for opening a session.  In this case, calls to
close the session will not actually release the resources
associated with the session until the reference count falls to
zero.

A RuntimeError is raised if the client_pid does not have an
open session.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformCloseSessionAdmin">
      <arg direction="in" name="client_pid" type="i">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Linux PID of the client thread
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Close an active session for the client process completely.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>This administrative function is used to forcibly close an
active session regardless of the client's reference count.
Similarly, if a client process PID is no longer active, but an
open session exists, this implementation is used to release
the session resources.

When closing a write-mode session, the control values that were
recorded when the session was promoted to write-mode are restored.
A RuntimeError is raised if the client_pid does not have an
open session.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformStartBatch">
      <arg direction="in" name="signal_config" type="a(iis)">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>domain_type (int): One of the geopmpy.topo.DOMAIN_*
                   integers corresponding to a domain
                   type to read from.

domain_idx (int): Specifies the particular domain
                  index to read from.

signal_name (str): The name of the signal to read.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="control_config" type="a(iis)">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>domain_type (int): One of the geopmpy.topo.DOMAIN_*
                   integers corresponding to a domain
                   type to write to.

domain_idx (int): Specifies the particular domain
                  index to write to.

control_name (str): The name of the control to write.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" name="batch" type="(is)">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>tuple(int, str):
server_pid (int): The Linux PID of the batch server process.

server_key (str): A unique identifier enabling the
                  server/client connection across
                  inter-process shared memory.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Start a batch server to support a client session.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Configure the signals and controls that will be enabled by the
batch server and start the server process.  The server enables
fast access for the signals and controls that are configured
by the caller.  These are configured by specifying a name,
domain and domain index for each of the signals and controls
that the server will support.

After a batch server is successfully created, the client will
interact with the batch server though PlatformIO interfaces
that do not go over DBus.  That is, once access is established
by DBus, a faster protocol can be safely used.

The batch server does not enable features beyond those of
the read_signal() or write_control() methods; it simply
provides a much higher performance interface.

A RuntimeError is raised if the client does not have
permission to read or write any of configured signals or
controls or if the client_pid does not have an open session.
The server process will not be created if any error occurs.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformStopBatch">
      <arg direction="in" name="server_pid" type="i">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Linux PID of the client thread.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>End a batch server previously started by the client.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Terminate the batch server process and free up all resources
associated with the batch server.  Any future calls by the
client to interfaces that require the batch server will result
in errors.

The batch server will also be terminated if the client session
that created the server terminates for any reason.

A RuntimeError will be raised if the specified server PID was
not previously created by the client's call to start_batch(),
or if the batch server has already been closed for any reason.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformReadSignal">
      <arg direction="in" name="signal_name" type="s">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Linux PID of the client thread.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="domain" type="i">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Name of the signal to read.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="domain_idx" type="i">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>One of the geopmpy.topo.DOMAIN_* integers
corresponding to a domain type to read from.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" name="sample" type="d">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>The value of the signal in SI units.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Read a signal from a particular domain.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Select a signal by name and read the current value from the
domain type and index specified.  The value is returned
as a floating point number in SI units.

A RuntimeError is raised if the client_pid does not have an
open session or if the client does not have permission to read the
signal from the specified domain.

A RuntimeError is raised if the requested signal is not
supported, the domain is invalid or the domain index is out of
range.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformWriteControl">
      <arg direction="in" name="control_name" type="s">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Linux PID of the client thread.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="domain" type="i">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>The name of the control to write.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="domain_idx" type="i">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>One of the geopmpy.topo.DOMAIN_* integers
corresponding to a domain type to written
to.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="in" name="setting" type="d">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Specifies the particular domain index to
write to.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Write a control value to a particular domain.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Select a control by name and write a new setting for the
domain type and index specified.  The written control setting
is a floating point number in SI units.

A RuntimeError is raised if the client_pid does not have an
open session, or if the client does not have permission to write the
control to the specified domain.

A RuntimeError is raised if a different client currently has an
open write-mode session.

A RuntimeError is raised if the requested control is not
supported, the domain is invalid or the domain index is out of
range.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformRestoreControl">
     <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Restore all controls recorded at the start of a session.
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>For the session associated to the given process, restore the state
of all controls, which is recorded at the beginning of the session.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformStartProfile">
      <arg direction="in" name="profile_name" type="s">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Name of application that PID supports
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Begin profiling a user PID
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Called by a thread to enable profiling as part of a named
application.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformStopProfile">
      <arg direction="in" name="region_names" type="as">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Names of all regions entered.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Stop profiling a user PID
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Called by a thread to end profiling as part of a named
application.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformGetProfilePids">
      <arg direction="in" name="profile_name" type="s">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Name of application that PID supports
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" name="pids" type="ai">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>All PID associated with profile_name or empty
list if profile_name is not registered.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Get PIDs associated with an application
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Called by a profiling thread to find all PIDs associated with
a named application.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
    <method name="PlatformPopProfileRegionNames">
      <arg direction="in" name="profile_name" type="s">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>Name of application that PID supports
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <arg direction="out" name="region_names" type="as">
        <doc:doc>
          <doc:summary>All region names associated with profile_name
or empty list if profile_name is not
registered.
          </doc:summary>
        </doc:doc>
      </arg>
      <doc:doc>
        <doc:description>
          <doc:summary>Get region names associated with an application
          </doc:summary>
          <doc:para>Called by a profiling thread to find all region names
associated with a named application.
          </doc:para>
        </doc:description>
      </doc:doc>
    </method>
  </interface>
</node>
